Guide to the Jack Gutzeit Amateur Radio Operator Records 1940s-2001 (bulk, 1970s-1990s) PR 418
New-York Historical Society
Jack Gutzeit amateur radio operator records
1940s-2001 (bulk, 1970s-1990s)
New-York Historical Society
Gutzeit, Jack, -2003
PR 418
5.21 Linear feet in 5 record cartons + 1 document box
The collection includes records compiled during much of Jack Gutzeit's (1921-2003) lifelong avocation as an amateur radio operator, operating primarily under the call sign W2LZX. The bulk of the collection includes about 12,000 QSL cards sent to Gutzeit from operators around the world, along with many of his transmission logs and some other documents related to ham radio operator activities.
Arrangement
The bulk of the collection consists of QSL cards and these remain in the order as received by N-YHS. These are generally sorted between cards received from United States and non-United States operators, then by prefix. A small addition to the collection was received later in 2021 and is appended as box 6 content.
Biographical / Historical
Jacob M. "Jack" Gutzeit (1921-2003) was, in the context of this collection, an amateur radio operator, known by the call sign W2LZX. He was born and raised in Brooklyn, NY, and as a married man in the 1940s, moved to Flushing, Queens, where he lived for 60 years. He died in Delray Beach, Florida.
Gutzeit became interested in electronics as a teenager and built his own radio tubes. He became a licensed amateur, or "ham," radio operator in 1939. During World War II, Gutzeit enlisted with the Army in 1943 and was assigned to the 897th Signal Company in the Pacific theater. After the 897th was assigned to the Air Force's 81st Air Depot group, he served as a radioman on B-17s. He was discharged from the military at the end of the war at the rank of sergeant.
Gutzeit was engaged with electronics throughout his life, as a teacher at Brooklyn Technical School, as a salesman of electronic devices and components, and as senior advertising manager for QSL Magazine. He obtained a private pilot's license in the 1950s, flying a Cessna 172 along the East Coast. He was an award-winning radio operator and a member of the American Radio Relay League (ARRL).
Gutzeit married Ruth Rakoff in 1942, shortly before heading to war. They had two children, Sande and Howard; Sande arranged the donation of this collection to N-YHS.
(The above note is based on a biographical note included by the donor with the collection.)
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Sande Gutzeit Levine, 2021
Scope and Contents
The collection includes records compiled during much of Jack Gutzeit's career as an amateur radio operator. These primarily include QSL cards sent to Gutzeit from around the world, acknowledging his transmissions. By the donor's count, there are 12,034 cards. The bulk of the cards were directed to Gutzeit's call sign of W2LZX; about 1200 were directed to four other call signs Gutzeit used when operating under other licenses at offshore locations in the Caribbean. The cards were skimmed during processing for date range; the bulk appears to be from the 1970s-1990s, with a few extending back to the 1940s. Beyond the essential facts of the acknowledged transmission, the cards portray a variety of artwork, photographs, and text that center variously on the originating locale and/or radio operator/team of operators.
The collection also holds Gutzeit's logs of transmissions from 1974-2001, with earlier logs for a brief period in 1955 and in 1960-65. There are also a few documents related to ham operator organizations, Gutzeit's personal QSL cards, a collage compiled by his niece of images of some of his cards, and photographs of operators.
Amateur radio stations.; Radio operators.; Logbooks.; Postcards.
- QSL cards. Amateur radio prefixes 1AO - 9Z4 (International) (Offsite-box 1, Box 1A)
- QSL cards. Amateur radio prefixes A - DL7 (International) (Offsite-box 1, Box 1B)
- QSL cards. Amateur radio prefixes DL8 - FY7 (International) (Offsite-box 1, Box 1C)
- QSL cards. Amateur radio prefixes G - HA (International) (Offsite-box 1, Box 1D)
- QSL cards. Amateur radio prefixes HB9 - JA0 (International) (Offsite-box 2, Box 2A)
- QSL cards. Amateur radio prefixes JD1 - OK3 (International) (Offsite-box 2, Box 2B)
- QSL cards. Amateur radio prefixes OA - SX (International) (Offsite-box 2, Box 2C)
- QSL cards. Amateur radio prefixes OK3 - UA2 (International) (Offsite-box 2, Box 2D)
- QSL cards. Amateur radio prefixes UA3 - UZ6 (International) (Offsite-box 3, Box 3A)
- QSL cards. Amateur radio prefixes V2A - YU1 (International) (Offsite-box 3, Box 3B)
- QSL cards. Amateur radio prefixes YU2 - ZZ6 (International) and U.S. Territories, Etc. (Offsite-box 3, Box 3C)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes Puerto Rico, Guam, U.S. Virgin Islands, and other U.S. territories, and other U.S. presence overseas (e.g., Antartica, Guantanamo Bay, Okinawa).
- QSL cards. Gutzeit operating offshore with other licenses (1 of 2), 1981 (Offsite-box 3, Box 3C)
  Includes Gutzeit operating with license 8P6CQ, Barbados, Feb. 1981 (US contacts).
- QSL cards. Gutzeit operating offshore with other licenses (2 of 2), 1981-1987 (Offsite-box 3, Box 3D)
  Includes 8P6CQ, Barbados, Feb 1981 (international contacts); ZF2FU,Caymans, Feb 1982, US and international contacts; J6LJG, St. Lucia, Feb 1984, US and international contacts; and C6ARD, Bahamas, Feb 1987, US and international contacts.
- QSL cards from the United States (Offsite-box 4, Box 4A, 4B)
- Additional QSL cards, international and United States (2 folders), 1970s-1990s (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-2)
  Holds additional cards received in late 2021.
- Amateur radio operator logs, 1974-1993 (Offsite-box 5, Volume 1-4)
  4 binders of logs. One log includes some correspondence related to Gutzeit's participation with the CQ DX Awards Committee, 1978-80.
- Amateur radio operator log & scrapbook, 1983-1996 (Offsite-box 4, Volume 1)
  Binder that includes a log for 1994-January 1996. The second half of the binder is a scrapbook with: various covers of CQ Magazine (1984-1995); various clippings, some with photos of Gutzeit (1980s); photocopies of Gutzeit's amateur radio station license from the FCC, with assigned call letters W2LZX (issued March 13, 1939); various prefix and other lists; OWLS Membership List; LIDXA roster of full and honorary members (1994); Constitution and by-laws for the North Jersey DX Association (1990) and rosters, membership recruiting procedure, and other documents for that organization; American Radio Relay League documents, such as field representative nomination rules and DX Century Club rules and honor roll (all 1990s).
- Amateur radio operator log, 1996-1999, 2001 (Offsite-box 4)
- Gutzeit's logs while operating under other licenses, 1955, 1980s (Offsite-box 4)
  Includes 4 spiral logbooks for Gutzeit's transmissions as 8P6CQ, ZF2FU, J6LJG, and C6ARD. The log for J6LJG was used earlier by Gutzeit, with one page logging calls of January 1955.
- Gutzeit's log "while engaged in portable & mobile operation", 1960-1965 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4)
- List of amateur radio prefixes, undated (Offsite-box 4)
  Annotated, likely to show those prefixes that Gutzeit connected with and that have QSL cards in the collection. Attached is a donor-supplied count of the cards by broad category.
- Gutzeit biographical note and personal QSL cards, circa 1939-1980s (Offsite-box 4)
  Includes Gutzeit's original QSL card (with his Carroll Street, Brooklyn address), his later card with his Flushing, Queens address, and his cards for his St. Lucia and Bahamas call letters. Also includes a biographical sketch of Gutzeit provided by the donor.
- "W2LZX", 2007 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5)
  Booklet of images of collaged QSL cards from the Gutzeit collection, compiled by his niece, Mindy Belloff, 2007, who wrote a foreword and added comments at points. Booklet numbered #8.
- Certificates, 1975, 1986 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 6)
  Certificates recognizing Gutzeit's achievement in contacting all 6 recognized continental areas of the world.
- Photographs, 1970s-1990s (Offsite-box 6, Folder 3)
  Photos of various radio operators
- Miscellaneous print matter, 1978, 1984, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 7)
  Holds one issue of "The DX'ers magazine" (issue #589, Jan. 2, 1984); "The Radio Amateur's World Map"; tearsheet of article "Das Anti-Radar" (1978, in German); CQ stationery (envelope).